Cling on Android

Cling Core provides a UPnP stack for Android applications. Typically you'd write control point applications, as most Android systems today are small hand-held devices. You can however also write UPnP server applications on Android, all features of Cling Core are supported.

Cling on the Android emulator

At the time of writing, receiving UDP Multicast datagrams was not supported by the Android emulator. The emulator will send (multicast) UDP datagrams, however. You will be able to send a multicast UPnP search and receive UDP unicast responses, therefore discover existing running devices. You will not discover devices which have been turned on after your search, and you will not receive any message when a device is switched off. Other control points on your network will not discover your local Android device/services at all. All of this can be confusing when testing your application, so unless you really understand what works and what doesn't, you might want to use a real device instead.

This chapter explains how you can integrate Cling with your Android application as a shared Android application service component.

Configuring the application service

You can instantiate the Cling UpnpService in your Android application's main activity. On the other hand, if several activities in your application require access to the UPnP stack, a better design would utilize a background android.app.Service. Any activity that wants to access the UPnP stack can then bind and unbind from this service as needed.

The interface of this service component is org.fourthline.cling.android.AndroidUpnpService:

public interface AndroidUpnpService {
    public UpnpService get();
    public UpnpServiceConfiguration getConfiguration();
    public Registry getRegistry();
    public ControlPoint getControlPoint();
}

An activity typically accesses the Registry of known UPnP devices or searches for and controls UPnP devices with the ControlPoint.

You have to configure the built-in implementation of this service component in your AndroidManifest.xml:

    
    
    
    

    

        
            ...
        

        

    

The Cling UPnP service requires access to the WiFi interface on the device, this is in fact the only network interface on which it will bind. The service will automatically detect when the WiFi interface is switched off and handle this situation gracefully: Any client operation will result in a "no response from server" state, which your code has to expect anyway.

The service component starts and stops the UPnP system when the service component is created and destroyed. This depends on how you access the service component from within your activities.

Accessing the service from an activity

The lifecycle of services in Android is well defined. The first activity which binds to a service will start the service if it is not already running. When no activity is bound to the service any more, the operating system will destroy the service.

Let's write a simple UPnP browsing activity. It shows all devices on your network in a list and it has a menu option which triggers a search action. The activity connects to the UPnP service and then listens to any device additions or removals in the registry, so the displayed list of devices is kept up-to-date.

This is the skeleton of the activity class:

import android.app.ListActivity;
import android.content.ComponentName;
import android.content.Context;
import android.content.Intent;
import android.content.ServiceConnection;
import android.os.Bundle;
import android.os.IBinder;
import android.view.Menu;
import android.view.MenuItem;
import android.widget.ArrayAdapter;
import android.widget.Toast;
import org.fourthline.cling.android.AndroidUpnpService;
import org.fourthline.cling.android.AndroidUpnpServiceImpl;
import org.fourthline.cling.model.meta.Device;
import org.fourthline.cling.model.meta.LocalDevice;
import org.fourthline.cling.model.meta.RemoteDevice;
import org.fourthline.cling.registry.DefaultRegistryListener;
import org.fourthline.cling.registry.Registry;

public class UpnpBrowser extends ListActivity {

    private ArrayAdapter listAdapter;

    private AndroidUpnpService upnpService;

    private ServiceConnection serviceConnection = ...

    private RegistryListener registryListener = new BrowseRegistryListener();

    @Override
    public void onCreate(Bundle savedInstanceState) {
        super.onCreate(savedInstanceState);

        listAdapter =
            new ArrayAdapter(
                this,
                android.R.layout.simple_list_item_1
            );
        setListAdapter(listAdapter);

        getApplicationContext().bindService(
            new Intent(this, AndroidUpnpServiceImpl.class),
            serviceConnection,
            Context.BIND_AUTO_CREATE
        );
    }

    @Override
    protected void onDestroy() {
        super.onDestroy();
        if (upnpService != null) {
            upnpService.getRegistry().removeListener(registryListener);
        }
        getApplicationContext().unbindService(serviceConnection);
    }

    ...

}

We utilize the default layout provided by the Android runtime and the ListActivity superclass. Note that this activity can be your applications main activity, or further up in the stack of a task. The listAdapter is the glue between the device additions and removals on the Cling Registry and the list of items shown in the user interface.

The upnpService variable is null when no backend service is bound to this activity. Binding and unbinding occurs in the onCreate() and onDestroy() callbacks, so the activity is bound to the service as long as it is alive.

Pausing the UPnP service in the background

When an activity is no longer active (in stopped or paused state) it will still be bound to the UPnP service. The UPnP service will continue running, even if your application is not visible anymore. This will consume CPU time and power on your device, as the UPnP service's registry has to periodically maintain discovered devices, refresh announcements of local devices, remove expired GENA event subscriptions, and so on. You can tell the UPnP service to no longer maintain its registry by calling Registry#pause() when your activity's onPause() or onStop() method is called. You can then resume the background service maintenance with Registry#resume(), or check the status with Registry#isPaused(). Please read the Javadoc of these methods for more details and what consequences pausing registry maintenance has on devices, services, and GENA subscriptions.

Binding and unbinding the service is handled with this ServiceConnection:

private ServiceConnection serviceConnection = new ServiceConnection() {

    public void onServiceConnected(ComponentName className, IBinder service) {
        upnpService = (AndroidUpnpService) service;

        // Refresh the list with all known devices
        listAdapter.clear();
        for (Device device : upnpService.getRegistry().getDevices()) {
            registryListener.deviceAdded(device);
        }

        // Getting ready for future device advertisements
        upnpService.getRegistry().addListener(registryListener);

        // Search asynchronously for all devices
        upnpService.getControlPoint().search();
    }

    public void onServiceDisconnected(ComponentName className) {
        upnpService = null;
    }
};

First, all UPnP devices that are already known can be queried and displayed (there might be none if the UPnP service was just started and no device has so far announced its presence.)

Next a listener is registered with the Registry of the UPnP service. This listener will process additions and removals of devices as they are discovered on your network, and update the items shown in the user interface list. The BrowseRegistryListener is removed when the activity is destroyed.

Finally, you start asynchronous discovery by sending a search message to all UPnP devices, so they will announce themselves. Note that this search message is NOT required every time you connect to the service. It is only necessary once, to populate the registry with all known devices when your (main) activity and application starts.

This is the BrowseRegistryListener, its only job is to update the displayed list items:

class BrowseRegistryListener extends DefaultRegistryListener {

    @Override
    public void remoteDeviceDiscoveryStarted(Registry registry, RemoteDevice device) {
        deviceAdded(device);
    }

    @Override
    public void remoteDeviceDiscoveryFailed(Registry registry, final RemoteDevice device, final Exception ex) {
        runOnUiThread(new Runnable() {
            public void run() {
                Toast.makeText(
                        BrowseActivity.this,
                        "Discovery failed of '" + device.getDisplayString() + "': " +
                                (ex != null ? ex.toString() : "Couldn't retrieve device/service descriptors"),
                        Toast.LENGTH_LONG
                ).show();
            }
        });
        deviceRemoved(device);
    }

    @Override
    public void remoteDeviceAdded(Registry registry, RemoteDevice device) {
        deviceAdded(device);
    }

    @Override
    public void remoteDeviceRemoved(Registry registry, RemoteDevice device) {
        deviceRemoved(device);
    }

    @Override
    public void localDeviceAdded(Registry registry, LocalDevice device) {
        deviceAdded(device);
    }

    @Override
    public void localDeviceRemoved(Registry registry, LocalDevice device) {
        deviceRemoved(device);
    }

    public void deviceAdded(final Device device) {
        runOnUiThread(new Runnable() {
            public void run() {
                DeviceDisplay d = new DeviceDisplay(device);
                int position = listAdapter.getPosition(d);
                if (position >= 0) {
                    // Device already in the list, re-set new value at same position
                    listAdapter.remove(d);
                    listAdapter.insert(d, position);
                } else {
                    listAdapter.add(d);
                }
            }
        });
    }

    public void deviceRemoved(final Device device) {
        runOnUiThread(new Runnable() {
            public void run() {
                listAdapter.remove(new DeviceDisplay(device));
            }
        });
    }
}

For performance reasons, when a new device has been discovered, we don't wait until a fully hydrated (all services retrieved and validated) device metadata model is available. We react as quickly as possible and don't wait until the remoteDeviceAdded() method will be called. We display any device even while discovery is still running. You'd usually not care about this on a desktop computer, however, Android handheld devices are slow and UPnP uses several bloated XML descriptors to exchange metadata about devices and services. Sometimes it can take several seconds before a device and its services are fully available. The remoteDeviceDiscoveryStarted() and remoteDeviceDiscoveryFailed() methods are called as soon as possible in the discovery process. By the way, devices are equal (a.equals(b)) if they have the same UDN, they might not be identical (a==b).

Note that the Registry will call the listener methods in a separate thread. You have to update the displayed list data in the thread of the user interface.

The following two methods on the activity add a menu with a search action, so a user can refresh the list manually:

@Override
public boolean onCreateOptionsMenu(Menu menu) {
    menu.add(0, 0, 0, R.string.search_lan)
        .setIcon(android.R.drawable.ic_menu_search);
    return true;
}

@Override
public boolean onOptionsItemSelected(MenuItem item) {
    if (item.getItemId() == 0 && upnpService != null) {
        upnpService.getRegistry().removeAllRemoteDevices();
        upnpService.getControlPoint().search();
    }
    return false;
}

Finally, the DeviceDisplay class is a very simple JavaBean that only provides a toString() method for rendering the list. You can display any information about UPnP devices by changing this method:

class DeviceDisplay {
    Device device;

    public DeviceDisplay(Device device) {
        this.device = device;
    }

    public Device getDevice() {
        return device;
    }

    @Override
    public boolean equals(Object o) {
        if (this == o) return true;
        if (o == null || getClass() != o.getClass()) return false;
        DeviceDisplay that = (DeviceDisplay) o;
        return device.equals(that.device);
    }

    @Override
    public int hashCode() {
        return device.hashCode();
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        // Display a little star while the device is being loaded
        return device.isFullyHydrated() ? device.getDisplayString() : device.getDisplayString() + " *";
    }
}

We have to override the equality operations as well, so we can remove and add devices from the list manually with the DeviceDisplay instance as a convenient handle.

Optimizing service behavior

The UPnP service consumes memory and CPU time while it is running. Although this is typically not an issue on a regular machine, this might be a problem on an Android handset. You can preserve memory and handset battery power if you disable certain features of the Cling UPnP service, or if you even pause and resume it when appropriate.

Furthermore, some Android handsets do not support multicast networking (HTC phones, for example), so you have to configure Cling accordingly on such a device and disable most of the UPnP discovery protocol.

Tuning registry maintenance

There are several things going on in the background while the service is running. First, there is the registry of the service and its maintenance thread. If you are writing a control point, this background registry maintainer is going to renew your outbound GENA subscriptions with remote services periodically. It will also expire and remove any discovered remote devices when the drop off the network without saying goodbye. If you are providing a service, your device announcements will be refreshed by the registry maintainer and inbound GENA subscriptions will be removed if they haven't been renewed in time. Effectively, the registry maintainer prevents stale state on the UPnP network, so all participants have an up-to-date view of all other participants, and so on.

By default the registry maintainer will run every second and check if there is something to do (most of the time there is nothing to do, of course). The default Android configuration however has a default sleep interval of five seconds, so it is already consuming less background CPU time - while your application might be exposed to somewhat outdated information. You can further tune this setting by overriding the getRegistryMaintenanceIntervalMillis() in the UpnpServiceConfiguration. On Android, you have to subclass the service implementation to provide a new configuration:

public class MyUpnpService extends AndroidUpnpServiceImpl {

    @Override
    protected AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration createConfiguration(WifiManager wifiManager) {
        return new AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration(wifiManager) {

            @Override
            public int getRegistryMaintenanceIntervalMillis() {
                return 7000;
            }

        };
    }
}

Don't forget to configure MyUpnpService in your AndroidManifest.xml now instead of the original implementation. You also have to use this type when binding to the service in your activities.

Pausing and resuming registry maintenance

Another more effective but also more complex optimization is pausing and resuming the registry whenever your activities no longer need the UPnP service. This is typically the case when an activity is no longer in the foreground (paused) or even no longer visible (stopped). By default any activity state change has no impact on the state of the UPnP service unless you bind and unbind from and to the service in your activities lifecycle callbacks.

In addition to binding and unbinding from the service you can also pause its registry by calling Registry#pause() when your activity's onPause() or onStop() method is called. You can then resume the background service maintenance (thread) with Registry#resume(), or check the status with Registry#isPaused().

Please read the Javadoc of these methods for more details and what consequences pausing registry maintenance has on devices, services, and GENA subscriptions. Depending on what your application does, this rather minor optimization might not be worth dealing with these effects. On the other hand, your application should already be able to handle failed GENA subscription renewals, or disappearing remote devices!

Configuring discovery

The most effective optimization is selective discovery of UPnP devices. Although the UPnP service's network transport layer will keep running (threads are waiting and sockets are bound) in the background, this feature allows you to drop discovery messages selectively and quickly.

For example, if you are writing a control point, you can drop any received discovery message if it doesn't advertise the service you want to control - you are not interested in any other device. On the other hand if you only provide devices and services, all discovery messages (except search messages for your services) can probably be dropped, you are not interested in any remote devices and their services at all.

Discovery messages are selected and potentially dropped by Cling as soon as the UDP datagram content is available, so no further parsing and processing is needed and CPU time/memory consumption is significantly reduced while you keep the UPnP service running even in the background on an Android handset.

To configure which services are supported by your control point application, override the service implementation as shown in the previous section and provide an array of ServiceType instances:

public class MyUpnpService extends AndroidUpnpServiceImpl {

    @Override
    protected AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration createConfiguration(WifiManager wifiManager) {
        return new AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration(wifiManager) {

            @Override
            public ServiceType[] getExclusiveServiceTypes() {
                return new ServiceType[] {
                        new UDAServiceType("SwitchPower")
                };
            }

        };
    }
}

This configuration will ignore any advertisement from any device that doesn't also advertise a schemas-upnp-org:SwitchPower:1 service. This is what our control point can handle, so we don't need anything else. If instead you'd return an empty array (the default behavior), all services and devices will be discovered and no advertisements will be dropped.

If you are not writing a control point but a server application, you can return null in the getExclusiveServiceTypes() method. This will disable discovery completely, now all device and service advertisements are dropped as soon as they are received.

Another problem with UPnP discovery are bad quality Android devices (HTC) which might not support multicast networking. If you see a discovered remote device disappear from the Cling registry after a short time (a few minutes), but the device is cleary still connected to the network, you most likely have this issue. Your control point does not receive the periodic multicast heartbeat alive messages from remote devices. You have to disable remote device expiration in the Cling configuration and manually remove remote devices from the registry whenever you think they are expired. Read the Javadoc of the method UpnpServiceConfiguration#getRemoteDeviceMaxAgeSeconds() and override it accordingly as shown in the previous example.